When I think about the rise of AI, I'm reminded by the rise of literacy.
A few hundred years ago, many people in society thought that maybe not everyone needed to
be able to read and write.
Back then, many people were attending fused or hurting sheep, so maybe there was less
need for written communication.
And all that was needed was for the high priest and priestesses and monks to be able to
read the holy book, and the rest of us could just go to the temple or church or the holy
building and sit and listen to the high priest and priestesses read to us.
Fortunately, we're since figured out that we can build a much richer society if lots
of people can read and write.
Today, AI is in the hands of the high priest and priestesses.
These are the highly skilled AI engineers, many of whom work on the big tech companies.
And most people have access only to the AI that they build for them.
I think that we can build a much richer society if we can enable everyone to help to write
the future.
But why is AI largely concentrated in the big tech companies?
Because many of these AI projects have been expensive to build.
They may require dozens of high-disco engineers and it may cost millions or tens of millions
of dollars to build an AI system.
And the large tech companies, particularly the ones with hundreds of millions or even
billions of users, have been better than anyone else at making these investments pay off.
Because for them, one size fits all AI systems, such as one that improves web search or that
recommends that the products for online shopping can be applied to this very large number of
users to generate a massive amount of revenue.
But this recipe for AI does not work once you go outside to tech and internet sectors to
other places where, for the most part, there are hardly any projects that apply to a hundred
million people or that generates comparable economics.
Let me illustrate an example.
Many weekends, I drive a few minutes from my house to a local pizza store to buy a slice
of Hawaiian pizza from the gentleman that owns this pizza store.
And his pizza is great.
But he always has a lot of coat, pizza sitting around.
And every weekend, some different flavor of pizza is all the style.
But when I wash him off of his store, I get excited because by selling pizza, he is generating
data.
And this is data that he can take advantage of if he had access to AI.
AI systems are good at spotting patterns when given access to the right data.
And perhaps an AI system could spot if Mediterranean pizzas sell really well on a Friday night,
because it suggested him to make more of it on a Friday afternoon.
Now you might say to me, hey Andrew, this is a small pizza store.
What's the big deal?
And I say to the gentleman that owns this pizza store, something that could help him improve
his revenues by a few thousand dollars a year that will be a huge deal to him.
I know that there is a lot of hype about AI's need for massive data sets.
And having more data does help, but contrary to the hype, AI can often work just fine even
on models and models of data, such as the data generated by a single pizza store.
So the real problem is not that there isn't enough data from the pizza store.
The real problem is that the small pizza store could never serve enough customers to justify
the cost of hiring an AI team.
I know that in the United States, there are about half a million independent restaurants, and
collectively, these restaurants do serve tens of millions of customers.
But every restaurant has difference with a different menu, different customers, different
ways of recording sales that no one size fits our AI will work for all of them.
What would it be like if we could enable small businesses and especially local businesses
to use AI?
Let's take a look at what it might look like at a company that makes and sells t-shirts.
I would love if an accountant working for the t-shirt company can use AI for demand forecasting,
say figure out what funny means the print on t-shirts that would drive sales by looking
at what's trending on social media.
Or for product placement, why can't a front-to-store manager take pictures of what the store
looks like and show it to an AI and have an AI recommend where to place products to improve
sales?
Supply chain?
Can an AI recommend a buyer whether or not they should pay $20 per yard for a piece of
fabric now or if they should keep looking because they might be defined at cheaper elsewhere?
Or quality control?
A quality inspector should be able to use AI to automatically scan pictures of the fabric
they used to make t-shirts to check if there are any tears or discolourations in the
cloth.
Today, large tech companies routinely use AI to solve problems like these and to grade
effect.
But a typical t-shirt company or a typical auto mechanic or retailer or school or local
firm will be using AI for exactly zero of these applications today.
Every t-shirt maker is sufficiently different from every other t-shirt maker that there
is no one-size-bizel AI that will work for all of them.
And in fact, once you go outside the internet and tech sectors in other industries, even
large companies such as pharmaceutical companies, the car makers, hospitals also struggle with
this.
This is the long-tailed problem of AI.
If you were to take all current and potential AI projects and sort them in decreasing order
of value and plot them, you'd get grounded looks like this.
Either single-moles-validable AI system is something that decides what ads to show
people on the internet.
Maybe the second-moles-validable is a web search engine.
Maybe the third-moles-validable is an online shopping product recommendation system.
But when you go to the right of this curve, you then get projects like t-shirt product
placements or t-shirt demand forecasting or pizzeria demand forecasting.
And each of these is a unique project that needs to be custom built.
When t-shirt demand forecasting, it depends on trending memes on social media, it's a very
different project than pizzeria demand forecasting if that depends on the pizzeria sales data.
So today, there are millions of projects sitting on the tail of this distribution that no
one is working on, but whose aggregate value is massive.
So how can we enable small businesses and individuals to build AI systems that matter
to them?
Well, most of the last few decades, if you want to build an AI system, this is what you
have to do.
You have to write pages and pages of code.
And while I would love for everyone to learn to code, and in fact, online education and
also offline education are helping more people than ever learn to code, unfortunately, not
everyone has the time to do this.
But there is an emerging new way to build AI systems that will let more people participate.
Just as pen and paper, which are a vastly superior technology to stone, tablet and chisel,
were instrumental to widespread literacy, there are emerging new AI development platforms
that shift the focus from asking you to write lots of code, to asking you to focus on providing
data, and this turns out to be much easier for a lot of people to do.
Today, there are multiple companies working on platforms like these.
I want to illustrate a few of the concepts using one that my team has been building.
Take the example of an inspector wanting AI to help detect defects in fabric.
An inspector can take pictures of the fabric and upload it to a platform like this, and
they can go in to show the AI what tears in the fabric looks like by drawing rectangles.
And they can also go in to show the AI what discolourations in the fabric looks like by
drawing rectangles.
So these pictures together with the green and pink rectangles that the inspector's
drawing are data created by the inspector to explain to AI how to find tears and discolourations.
After the AI examines this data, we may find that it has seen enough pictures of tears,
but not yet enough pictures of discolourations.
This is akin to if a junior inspector had learned to rely on these spot tears, but still
needs to further hone the judgment about discolourations.
So the inspector can go back and take more pictures of discolourations to show to the
AI to help it deepen this understanding.
By adjusting the data you give to the AI, you can help the AI get smarter.
So an inspector using an accessible platform like this can in a few hours to a few days,
and with purchasing a suitable camera setup, be able to build a custom AI system to detect
defects, tears and discolourations in all the fabric being used to make teachers throughout
the factory.
And once again, you may say, hey, Andrew, this is one factory, like why is this a big deal?
And I say to you, does this a big deal to that inspector whose life this makes easier?
And equally, this type of technology can empower a baker to use AI to check for the quality
of the cakes they're making, or a organic farmer to check the quality of the vegetables,
or a furniture maker to check the quality of the wood they're using.
Platforms like these will probably still need a few more years before they're easy enough
to use for every Pizzeria owner, but many of these platforms are coming along, and some
of them are getting to be quite usable to someone that has tech savvy today with just
a bit of training.
But what this means is that rather than relying on the high-prease and pre-susages to write
AI systems for everyone else, we can start to empower every accountant, every store manager,
every buyer, and every whole team inspector to build their own AI systems.
I hope that the Pizzeria owner and many other small business owners like him will also take
advantage of this technology, because AI is creating tremendous wealth and will continue
to create tremendous wealth.
And it's only by democratizing access to AI that can ensure that this wealth is spread
far and wide across society.
Hundreds of years ago, I think hardly anyone understood the impact that widespread literacy
will have.
Today, I think hardly anyone understands the impact that democratizing access to AI will
have.
Building AI systems has been other reach for most people, but that does not have to be
the case.
In the coming era of AI, we will empower everyone to build AI systems for themselves, and I
think that will be a incredibly exciting future.
Thank you very much.